Guide to the Rick Bass Papers
The Wittliff Collections
Rick Bass Papers
1982-1994, undated
The Wittliff Collections
Bass, Rick
SWWC.020
4.5 Linear Feet
9 boxes Plus oversize
The Rick Bass papers are comprised of manuscripts, galley proofs, notes, clippings, correspondence, legal papers, photographs and artifacts, 1924 to the present, relating to Bass' career as a writer.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gifts of Rick Bass and Scott Slovic beginning in 1991.
Biographical Note
Novelist, essayist, and short story writer Rick Bass was born March 7, 1958 in Fort Worth, Texas. He was raised in Houston and graduated with a B.S. in Geology from Utah State University in 1979. Employed as a petroleum geologist in Mississippi from 1979 to 1987, Bass has since written full time on environmental issues and the vanishing wilderness. Bass has been an active environmentalist and member of the Sierra Club, Montana Wilderness Association, Cabinet Resources Group, Round River Conservation Studies, and the Yaak Valley Forest Council. He regularly publishes articles in magazines such as Field and Stream, Sports Afield, Gray's Sporting Journal, Outdoor Life, and others. Bass and his wife Elizabeth moved to Montana's Yaak Valley in 1987, where Bass finds the isolation he requires to write.
Describing Bass's storytelling voice, Leigh Tillman Partington writes that Bass tells a story "true, strong, and intimate; the details of his language are lush and pure, providing just the right amount of landscape and inner turmoil. Above all, his stories are about precarious balances: between men and women, children and adults, friends, lovers, and between humans and the natural world. His language reflects that balance. Like Eudora Welty, to whom he is often compared, Bass plays close attention to inner and outer surfaces, watching where and how they meet, and he captures those meeting places on the page" (Contemporary Southern Writers, 1999).
Scope and Contents
The Rick Bass papers are comprised of manuscripts, galley proofs, notes, clippings, correspondence, legal papers, photographs and artifacts, 1924 to the present, relating to Bass' career as a novelist. Series include Works, Clippings and Reviews, Writing Related Files, Environmental Concerns, General Correspondence, and Personal. The largest of these series is the first, Works, which is comprised mainly of photocopied pages from Bass' handwritten notebooks which serve as the forum for Bass' ideas and notes.
Authors, American -- 20th century; Environmentalism; Natural history literature; Bass, Rick
- Works, 1984-1994, undated
  Series Description
  This series surveys Bass' works from his earliest published pieces to his more recent articles and stories. In this series are manuscripts for The Watch, Oil Notes, The Ninemile Wolves, Winter: Notes from Montana, as well as notes for The Deer Pasture and short stories published in Platte River. The series also contains numerous short stories and essays, research notes, journal notes, reviews, and interviews. Most of the non-fiction manuscripts relate in some way to Bass' intense relationship with nature and concern for the environment, although they also concern his writing career.
  The bulk of this series is comprised of photocopied pages from the notebooks in which Bass does most of his writing, and also contains manuscript pages, typed drafts, computer disks, galley proofs, and published pieces, many of which are heavily annotated. Not all of the manuscripts are complete; many lack pages, while others contain only Bass' notes or are partially finished. It is important to note that the backs of his papers often contain notes to other manuscripts, correspondence, and other information, since Bass recycles paper by using both sides. Some notes are on scraps, and in one case, a note is written on a piece of bark. Sent to the Wittliff Collections in small pieces at a time, the manuscripts have been arranged alphabetically by the processor.
  - "The Afterlife," drafts, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alaska journal notes, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Angel," drafts, 1991, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Audubon, notes, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Barry Hannah, notes, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bedichek, notes, 1993, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Beloit, notes, 1993, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Caribou," typed draft, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Chances," draft, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Dark-Eyed Owl," third revision on floppy disk, September 29, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Deer Pasture," notes, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "A Dog in the Hand, and other pointers from the bird-dog man of Texas," in Esquire, October 1989 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "Dog Poem," for Amy Hempel, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "Earth Divers," first page of typed draft, May 1994 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Ferns," draft, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "Field Events," draft and notes, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "Field Stripping Arizona," in The Discovery Channel Magazine, June 1990 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Fire story, notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "First Snow, On the Road with Rick Bass," in The Climbing Art, Summer 1991 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "Four Coyotes," in Northern Lights, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - "Four Days," drafts, notes, and corrections, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - "Four Deer," drafts, 1993, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - "Grace," in Gray's Sporting Journal, Fall 1986 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Grant proposal, notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - "Green Valley," notes, drafts, 1994, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - "Grizzlies in Non-Fiction," draft, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Hawaii notes, "Paradise Rising," in Traveler, June 1993 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - History of Rodney in "Fireflies," drafts, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "Hounds", undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "Idaho," notes, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - "In the Loyal Mountains," draft (1985), published article in Southwest Review, 1985-1990 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "India," notes, drafts, 1993, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "The Indians," draft, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Interview with Doug Peacock, Jim Tolisan, and Dennis Sizemore, transcript, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - "Key West," notes, drafts, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "Krapweed," notes, draft, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "Mahatma Joe," notes, typed draft, 1993, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - McKibben, Bill, quote for his book <The Age of Missing Information, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - "Memphis," typed draft, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - "Mississippi," in The Cimarron Review, June 1987 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - "More Dennis Stories," notes, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Myths of Bears, typed draft, notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - "La Nalgai," notes, typed draft, 1988, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Ninemile Wolves, notes and drafts, 1991, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Ninemile Wolves, edited typescript drafts (pgs. 3-90), undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Ninemile Wolves, proof, 1992, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - "Northern Rockies," notes, drafts, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Notes for the Prade Ranch, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Oil Notes, typed draft, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Oil Notes, copy edited draft, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
  - "On Willow Creek," in L. A. Times Magazine, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "The Other Fort Worth Basses," drafts, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - "Out on the Wild Fringe," in Audubon, January-February 1994 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - "Peacock"/ "San Juans," notes, drafts, 1993-1994, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - "The Perfect Day," notes, drafts, 1993, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Plans, notes, 1993, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - "Plimpton," draft, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - "The Prisoners," drafts, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - "Quanah," draft, notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Quote for A Hunter's Road by Jim Fergus, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - "The Rage of the Squat Kings," disk and drafts, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - "Records," unpublished draft, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Review of Mao II by Don DeLillo, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Review of The Moon by Whale Light and Other Adventures Among Bats by Diane Ackerman, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Review of Our Happiness by Tom Jenks in The American Book Review, December 1991-January 1992 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Speech given at the Public Lands Forum in Mesa, Arizona, February 28, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - "Romania," notes, drafts, 1993, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - "Rust," draft, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - "Sea," notes, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Sierra article, draft, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - "The Silent Language," draft, 1993, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - "Stephanie," notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - "Swan Valley, Montana" draft, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - "Swans," drafts, 1992, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - "Twin Grizzly Peak," early typed draft, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Unidentified manuscripts and general notes, 1992-1994, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - "The Valley," draft, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - "Valley of the Crows" (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - "The Wait," draft, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - The Watch - Original publisher's draft, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - The Watch Master's set, first pass, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Master's set, second pass, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Master's set, confirmation, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - "What Was Once Life," floppy disk (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - "When a Publisher Dies," unfinished draft, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - "Where the Sea Used to Be," drafts, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - "The Windy Day," notes and published version in The Quarterly, Winter 1992 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Winter, drafts, notes, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - "Wolves in Fiction," in Northern Lights (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - "Woodthieves," notes, drafts, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - "Woods Where I Live," draft and published version in Scholastic Scope, January 14, 1994, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - "Writers at Work," notes, draft, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Clippings and Reviews, 1987-1994
  Materials in this series include clippings and reviews regarding works published by Bass, and have been arranged chronologically.
  - Reviews of The Watch, Winter: Notes from Montana, and Oil Notes, includes an interview with Bass in Kinesis, 1987-1991 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Reviews of Winter: Notes from Montana and The Ninemile Wolves, 1992-1994 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Reviews of Oil Notes, Wild to the Heart, Winter: Notes from Montana, and The Ninemile Wolves, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Writing Related Files, 1982-1994, undated
  These files are comprised of editorial correspondence regarding Bass' writing and its publication, correspondence and ephemera related to author readings and booksignings, course description and coursework related to fiction and non-fiction college writing courses taught by Bass, audiocassette tapes and a full transcript of an interview with Scott Slovic regarding Bass' writing career.
  - Correspondence with publishers and universities related to Bass' writing, 1982, 1991-1994 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Readings, book signings, and other appearances, 1988-1989, 1991-1993 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Teaching (University of Montana), includes syllabi, students' manuscripts, memos, notes, 1992, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Interview of Bass by Scott Slovic, cassettes and draft of published piece, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - General Materials, includes receipts, notes, business cards, etc. (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Environmental Concerns, 1990-1994
  Flyers, clippings, and correspondence in this series include letters to and from Bass regarding environmental legislation and policy.
  - Correspondence (to and from Bass), 1990-1994 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Flyers, clippings, and other promotional material, 1991-1994 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- General Correspondence, 1987-1993, undated
  Subjects in this series include oil and mineral leases and real estate transactions made by Rick Bass (1987-1988), while later correspondence is more general in nature, not related specifically to works by Bass.
  - Wittliff, Bill, 1991, undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - July-September, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - December 1987-January 1988 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - 1989-1993 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Personal, 1989-1993, undated
  This series is comprised of memorabilia such as dog medical records and hunting licenses, travel documents, childhood and adult photographs of Bass, family papers and news clippings.
  - Memorabilia, includes address book, dog's tag, hunting licenses, membership cards, insurance documents, notes, calendar, shopping list, etc. (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Travel, includes itineraries, guidebooks, maps, correspondence, 1993, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Photographs, childhood and with wife, 1989, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Family papers, includes father's draft card, clippings of articles written by his father, receipts, etc. (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Clippings and articles (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - General papers, University of Mississippi newsletters, financial documents, listing for Bass' ranch, miscellaneous documents (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Originals of photocopied clippings (Box 9, Folder 8)
- Artifacts, undated
  This series includes personal effects of Bass such as a chainsaw blade, notes he wrote on a piece of tree back, two Walkman radios, and two old license plates.
  - Chainsaw blade (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - License plates (Box 10, Folder 2-3)
  - Notes on tree bark & Two Walkman radios, pens (Box 10, Folder 4)